Finding aid to the Frances Crowe papers SSC.MS.00249
Sophia Smith Collection
Frances Crowe papers
1960-2015
Sophia Smith Collection
Crowe, Frances, 1919-
SSC.MS.00249
61 boxes (74.25 linear feet)
Pacifist; Political activist. Papers document over twenty years of social activism in the Pioneer Valley of Western Massachusetts, including activities of local chapters of the American Friends' Service Committee, Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Women Against the War, War Resisters' League, and Amnesty International.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access: collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be somewhat difficult to use. Researchers must sign Access Agreement form agreeing to not identify living persons without their permission.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Frances Crowe in 1984-2017. The collection accession numbers are 84-31, 84-67, 95S-64, 97S-35, 00S-54, 03S-51, 08S-86, 15S-46, 16S-72, 16S-95, 2017S-015.
Biographical / Historical
Born Carthage, Missouri, 1919; graduated Stephens College (Columbia, MO), 1939; Syracuse University in 1941; graduate work, Columbia University and New School for Social Research. Married Thomas Crowe, 1945, and moved to Northampton, MA; three children. Active in the Society of Friends and the American Friends' Service Committee, particularly the Peace and Social Concerns Committee. Became Western Massachusetts Representative for the AFSC in 1980s. During the Vietnam War she worked as a draft counselor. In the 1960s, she founded the Northampton chapter of Women's International League for Peace and Freedom; the Sane Nuclear Policy Committee; and the Valley Peace Center in Amherst, MA. Also a founding member of the Traprock Peace Center, Deerfield, MA, and the Committee to End Apartheid, Springfield, MA. A peace activist since the bombing of Hiroshima, Crowe has participated in numerous protests which have led to arrests, trials, and imprisonment.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Related Materials
The records of the American Friends Service Committee of Western Massachusetts are in the Special Collections of the University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
Scope and Contents
Papers document over twenty years of social activism in the Pioneer Valley of Western Massachusetts, including activities of local chapters of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Women Against the War, War Resisters' League, and Amnesty International. Extensive records from Crowe's work as the western Massachusetts representative for American Friends' Service Committee (1970s-90s), and numerous subject files on a variety of causes. Writings, memorabilia, and printed material document her trip to China in 1974.
Pacifists--United States--Biography--Sources; Anti-apartheid movements--United States--History--Sources; Antinuclear movement--United States--History--Sources; Conscientious objectors--United States--History--Sources; Northampton (Mass.)--History--Sources; Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources; China--Description and travel--Sources; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Protest movements--Sources; Draft resisters--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Environmental protection--Citizen participation-History--20th century--Sources; Peace movements--History--20th century--Sources; correspondence; clippings; Newsletters; scrapbooks; photographs; diaries; Posters; Videotapes; memorabilia; Calendars; notebooks; Manuscripts; Notes; Speeches; Petitions; Itineraries; Financial records; Oral histories; Audiotapes; Awards; Computer media; DVD video discs; Diplomas; Legal documents; Pamphlets; Programs; American Friends Service Committee-Massachusetts--History--Sources; Crowe, Frances, 1919-; Crowe, Frances; Crowe, Frances
- Frances Crowe materials related to peace activism, 1986-2003; 2003-S-0051; 1.25 linear feet (1 box; three posters in flat file)
  - Materials related to Weapons Elimination Committee, 1994-1996; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - War Toys Exchange clippings and flyers, 1994; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Mount Toby Peace Restreat clippings and programs, 2000; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Daily Hampshire Gazette clippings about Crowe, 1998; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Peace activism materials, 1994-2002; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Interfaith Pilgrimage for Peace and Life flyers, notes, programs, 1994-1997; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Material related to anti-militarism in Northampton MA schools, 1998; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Women's Strike for Peace materials, 1995-200; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Women and Life on Earth Pentagon Action, 1999; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous materials related to Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1995-2000; undated; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous materials related to South Africa apartheid, divestment and reparation, 1986-2000; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Fatima Yandieva miscellaneous materials, 2000; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous materials concerning sanctions against Nigeria, 1997-2000; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Martin Luther King Commission, 1997; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Notes pertaining to New Party, 1993; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and notes regarding Middle East peace, 1995; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, children's artwork, miscellaneous materials related to Iraq, 2001; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - TLS by Bill Clinton and clippings related to Nicaragua, 1997; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous materials related to anthrax, 2001-2002; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Massachusetts Women's Congress for Peace materials, 2001-2002; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Emails, position papers, notes, flyers related to 9/11, 2001; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous materials related to terrorism, anti-terrorism, Patriot Act, 2001-2002; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Local organizations notes, artcicles, emails, miscellaneous materials, 2001-2003; 2003-S-0051 (Box 1)
- Frances Crowe personal papers including audiovisual materials, 1963-2015; 2015-S-0046; 4.25 linear feet (4 boxes. Other materials: Anti-war posters, MA house of representatives resolution (2008), Drawer 106. )
  DVD video discs; Videotapes; CDs
  - "Nuclear Spent Fuel & Homeland Security; The Case for Hardened Storage" DVD, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to seminar on nonviolence, 2004; 2015-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Frances Crowe interview transcripts conducted by son and grandchildren, 2008; 2015-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding death of husband, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers and photiographs, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Notebooks, 2001-2006; 2015-S-0046 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, photographs, correspondence, miscellaneous materials related to anti-war, pacifism, anti-nuclear, draft resistance and other activisms, 1963-2015; 2015-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Hyde family genealogy, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Retirement celebration, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1997; 2015-S-0046 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, notes and other materials, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - Legal papers from arrest at Vermont Yankee, 2011; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - Speeches and awards, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - "Weathering Hard times: an open discussion with those who did," Sunderland Energy Committee DVD, 2008; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous articles about Frances Crowe, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - Transcripts of audio interviews, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - Notes, drafts, publicity for "Finding My Radical Soul", undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - Chains used at Vermont Yankee protest, 2011; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - "Pritchard Crone or I, Arnold, Copy 2", 2000 July 23; 2015-S-0046 (Box 3)
  - "A Tribute to Frances Crowe Celebrating 27 years," and other miscellaneous DVDs, 1994; 2011; 2015-S-0046 (Box 4)
  - "Peaceful Woman, Fighting Hard: Peggy Seeger sings five peace songs in honor of Frances Crowe of Northampton, MA" CD, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous audiocassette interviews with Frances, 2008 August 28; 2015-S-0046 (Box 4)
  - DVD documentary of Vermont Yankee protest by Tim Wessel, 2006 October 16; 2015-S-0046 (Box 4)
  - "An Activist Life; Student Oral History Project," on three CDs, undated; 2015-S-0046 (Box 4)
  - Anti-war posters and MA House of Representatives resolution, 2008; undated; 2015-S-0046 (Mapcase 5)
    General
- Frances Crowe posters and protest signs, 1970-2010; 2016-S-0095; 1 accession (Flat files drawers 111-114)
  - Posters and signs American Friends Service Committee, anti-apartheid, gun violence, nuclear movement, war, 1970-2016; 2016-S-0095 (Mapcase 111)
  - Posters and signs biographical, black history, Bosnia, Central America, El Salvador, 1970-2016; 2016-S-0095 (Mapcase 112)
  - Posters and signs regarding healthcare, local events, peace and miscellaneous, 1970-2016; 2016-S-0095 (Mapcase 113)
  - Posters and signs regarding U.S.politics, Vietnam, women's rights, 1970-2016; 2016-S-0095 (Mapcase 114)
- Frances Crowe correspondence, writings, notes, photographs, memorabilia and miscellaneous materials, 1960-1997; 1997-S-0035; Crowe, Frances; 10 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Materials related to Rainbow Coalition, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 1)
  - South Africa and Coca Cola boycott materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 1)
  - "Crescent Street Irregulars", undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 1)
  - Valley Women's Union materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to nuclear test ban, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to El Salvador, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 1)
  - Martin Luther King Day materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings and memorabilia, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 1)
  - Western Mass Disarmament Working Group materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 2)
  - Materials related to film series, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 2)
  - Small runs of various periodicals, 1973-1989; 1997-S-0035 (Box 2)
  - Materials related to Grove Street Inn, Northampton, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 3)
  - Nuclear war and political trials miscellaneous materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 3)
  - Materials related to Central America, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 3)
  - AFSC Hiroshima/Nagasaki Day materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous petitions and other materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 3)
  - Haymarket People's Fund miscellaneous materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 3)
  - Materials related to civil defense and emergency management, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 3)
  - Nicaragua slides and other materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 4)
  - Amherst MA nuclear free zone materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 4)
  - Frances Crowe miscellaneous materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 4)
  - Materials related to Star Wars and nuclear freeze, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 5)
  - Local political issue materials, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings and flyers, undated; 1997-S-0035 (Box 5)